Guide to the Herbert F. Janick Jr. Papers MS 012
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
- Series 3: Subject Files, 38885
  - Oral Histories - Student Work - Introduction to Historical Research, 38894
    - Western Connecticut State University -- History., 38895
      - Marilyn Fagan (interview) Creator: Fagan, Marilyn Interviewer(s): Carolyn Billeb and Alexis Brancato Interview location: unknown Running time: 40 min., May 4, 1992; 38945; Number of tapes:1 [tape stock length: 90 minute] (Box 10, Item 20)
        Topics discussed: (side A): Beginning at WestConn; came in 1971 and worked in register's office until 1975; nursing department from 1975; 1976; worked for Dr. Feldman while he was Dean of the School of Business; Ancell School; division of 3 schools; business school began in 1976 at midtown campus; most classes held in White Hall; moved to Westside in 1982; Donation made by Ancell; school named after the business man; he was chairman of Ethan Allen; Dr. Feldman as president of WestConn; Growth of the business school; Contact w/ students; Budget cuts; all schools were hit hard by them; employees and faculty cut (Arts and Science probably more); Budget problem of 1970s; college didn't have paper because of budget problems; Faculty turnover; business school has had a lot of change; Unions at WestConn; recent lay offs, only clerical and non; faculty; she took early retirement; a few teachers were laid off during Dr. Haas' presidency; AAUP and AFT; Women's issues at business school; probably as many women to men in school now; beginning was mostly men; rising academic standards lead to more gender diversity; Relation w/ students; senior projects/seminars; College to university; attract more professors; academic executives; president change from Dr. Bersi to Dr. Feldman; Dr. Feldman leaving; Structure of the school administration; president has several vice presidents to help; Oral history project; Gertrude Braun; Nursing department; changeover in the head of nursing; involved w/ Danbury Hospital when she worked in department; Register's office; did all registrations by hand; Technology; computer improvement and computer labs; ATC project (Automated Technology Classroom); VAX computers; Westside; she wanted to stay and was going to miss Old Main; business school and education; MCS department; improved facilities; Field House; plans been around for awhile; has been built pretty quickly; Ella Grasso Hall; came after the classroom building; large; Commuter school; lack of dorm space; Growth of Western; development of Danbury and influx of business in area; increased prestige of Western; tuition; Reflection of her career; enjoyed her time at WestConn; Retirement; she was unhappy w/ working in general; not w/ WestConn; Change in students; seriousness of academics w/ higher admission standards; non; trads; MBA program; many students in the program; Her replacement; she trained her replacement; she had worked in graduate program before that; Personal relationship w/ students; students who worked for the business school; her niece went to WestConn
      - Claire Geddes (interview) Creator: Geddes, Claire Interviewer(s): (no name given) Interview location: unknown Running time: 30 min., Jun 14, 1905; 38944; Number of tapes:1 [tape stock length: 60 minute] (Box 10, Item 21)
        Coverage: 1944-1992
        Topics discussed: (side A): WestConn in 1940s; first job was in physical education; no men because of the war, but men had been here; the gym was in basement of Old Main; two tennis courts where student union is now; athletic field where Berkshire is now; only buildings on campus were Old Main and Fairfield Hall; Dr. Jenkins; was president when she arrived; dies shortly after she arrived; Dean of Women; appointed position by Dr. Haas after she became president; lived in Fairfield Hall; Various Committees; coordinated admissions; had role in scholarships; guidance committee; chair of screening committee; Men enter the school; came back after end of WW II; Al Geddes became Dean of Men and took charge of some of the committees; Dorm situation; always had problem w/ it; had full control over housing; checked all available housing before allowing students to go there; Litchfield Hall came while she was there; worked w/ architect; house mothers were needed; Newbury Hall came as well; drew up original plans for Grasso Hall; finally got chance to see it; Background; a year at Arnold College (now a division of University of Bridgeport); transferred to New College (experimental branch at Columbia); Master's at University of Michigan; started Doctorate at Columbia (never finished though); Coming to WestConn; had taught in East Hartford when Dr. Haas and Dr. Jenkins needed a physical education teacher; former teacher got job in red cross and recommended her; Changes after WW II; enrollment increased and that allowed more course offerings; they received music program as a specialty focus; nursing was unique at the college; business school last major difference; Returning students; title of Dean of Men and Women lasted until Dean of Students Affairs; Dorms; strict rules; no drinking or smoking; had to be in their rooms by a certain time; Tunnels; between Fairfield Hall and Higgins; held pipes for heating; Activities w/ the students in dorms; always had Christmas parties; always had to chaperone the girls; Age of majority; state lowered the age from 21 to 18; allowed drinking in dorms after that, but smoking (safety issue); Boys in dorms; boys weren't allowed above first floor lounges; when Litchfield Hall built, were allowed in rooms w/ doors open; became co; ed few years before she retired; Fairfield Hall experimented w/ becoming a separate men's dorm; Ratio of students to faculty; Enrollment before men; "Do; Day"; everyone worked on various projects to beautify campus; lead to Sing Night, proms and dances; WestConn today; has no connection w/ WestConn now; Political issues of the 1950s; 60s; never really a huge problem at WestConn; always had black students at school (although few in numbers); few protests and such; probably some male students avoiding draft; always more women than men; Dr. Haas; was great to work with and worked very closely w/ her; Tragic moments; Curley Hall named after Tom Curley, who died in hospital; Changes at WestConn; change in program (teacher's college to liberal arts); college to university; Westside campus; Dr. Burke; Dean of Student Affairs; Dr. Bersi; Attitude towards her job; Retirement; retired in 1976, year after Dr. Haas had retired; knows very few people there now; Interaction between administration and faculty
      - Claire Geddes (interview) Creator: Geddes, Claire Interviewer(s): John Denault and Gloria Barna Interview location: Geddes' home Running time: 40 min., Apr 30, 1991; 38943; Number of tapes:1 [tape stock length: 90 minute] (Box 10, Item 22)
        Coverage: 1940s-1991
        Topics discussed: (side A): Background (at WestConn); began in physical education as an assistant professor; spent most of her time at WestConn as Dean of Women; Background; grew up in New Haven; always wanted to be a teacher; went to Arnold College; later went to New College at Columbia; got her Master's at Michigan; Dean of Women; appointed to role after Dr. Haas became president in 1946; moved into Fairfield Hall; she became the dean shortly after she came to the college; Men at WestConn; began to come back after the war; Al Geddes came back and became Dean of Men; Al Geddes; worked together for eleven years before they "discovered" each other; he had been at Western before the WW II; Role as an Administrator; Changes at WestConn; college always tried to maintain standards; Views of the 1960s; events of the era came to campus later and they were prepared for them; Campus life; Dr. Haas got along well w/ everyone; family atmosphere; Dr. Haas; had an open door policy; Football; her physical education background, but had her reservations; the fieldhouse has always been talked about, but never built; Dr. Burton Cook was the man who really wanted it; Dr. Cook felt it would attract more attention to the college; Dr. Haas wasn't thrilled about it; Union at WestConn; before the Union, she would come to campus in summer and do work and wasn't paid for it; Family; she and Al Geddes have been married for over 30 years; didn't have children; took care of their parents; Life after WestConn; has traveled a lot since retiring; Dorm life; originally one dorm (Fairfield Hall) and only girls; ate their meals in dorm; had curfews they had to follow; men weren't allowed above the first floor in Fairfield Hall; "Do; Day"; occurred generally in the spring; skits were always done (this evolved into the Sing and Skit Nights); Interim Program; students did work in the area during the intersession (four week plan); all students had to participate in some life experience program; Outside experiences; most teachers in the area were graduates from the college; Teacher's College to Liberal Arts; originally an elementary education college, but then brought in secondary; music education became the specialty of WestConn; nursing came later as did other majors; Hatting industry; Danbury was primarily hatting when she first came; Land for the campus; never enough land; had to fight for the land for both Litchfield and Newbury; were fortunate to get the high school; Quonset Huts; instituted during "Do; Day"; Union began as she was retiring; Student government; was originally called CGA (Cooperative Government Association); comprised of both faculty and students, dues were paid by all members; later split into the faculty senate and SGA; Health Service; originally one nurse and a doctor on call
      - Dr. Alfred Geddes (interview) Creator: Geddes, Dr. Alfred Interviewer(s): Jonathan Bergen and John Hugo Interview location: Geddes' home Running time: 50 min., May 1, 1991; 38942; Number of tapes:1 [tape stock length: 60 minute] (Box 10, Item 23)
        Coverage: 1937-1991
        Topics discussed: (side A): Growth of Physical Education at WestConn; growth result of the time; teacher education school had influence on program; Basketball; men's varsity was already here; Mr. Pilkinton was the coach of the team; not sure if women's team was here or not at time; Recreation activities; tied in w/ education program; Small school; allowed for a close; knit family atmosphere; student government very active in putting together picnics; Development of sports teams; began after WW II; varsity team sports began after the war; varsity baseball one of the first to develop (coach a former pro player); Harvey Jessup; was hired around this time; Football; doesn't remember the first football game (in 1971); Berkshire Hall gym; original gym was a "matchbox"; half size of a basketball court; used Danbury High School gym for basketball games; never coached in the Berkshire Hall gym; Effects of WW II on college; more men started coming into college, many of them vets; the men were mature; "ERUTAM"; group of men who were career oriented; mature spelled backwards; WW II era vs. Vietnam era; there was a transition between WW II and Korean War; Vietnam had to do w/ college deferments; doesn't recall demonstrations; it was a peaceful campus; Dorms; weren't co; ed in the beginning; co; ed came after he retired in 1974; Relationship w/ other professors; diverse point of view is important to the campus; professional atmosphere; very good relationships; different generations; Dr. Jenkins; gentleman of the "old school"; he had the best of intentions; he was a leader; Dr. Haas; she took over after Dr. Jenkins died; she was acting president immediately after Jenkins' death; she was exceptionally good; great relationships w/ everyone he knew; good personality and capability; very appreciative of faculty and progress the men had made at college; invited to stay beyond mandatory year for retirement; Health Education; health curriculum can remember it always being there; health of student always priority; doctor on campus; Role of sports at college today; doesn't have a lot of contact w/ college now, only knows what he reads; different time and different mode; by 1930s, walk; on were normal and scholarships were still new; varsity teams and importance of winning; "Do; Day"; very enjoyable (side B): "Do; Day" (cont.); student government became cooperative government, it included faculty; it was a community service and had cooperative effort; it was almost like a "holiday atmosphere"; activities during day, skits and fun at night; Ruth Haas Library; library is heart of the university; college lucky someone saw need for a separate library; better facilities than previous; Development of sports at college; doesn't recall football; baseball and basketball was a nature development; the other three teacher colleges were all similar (although New Britain was a little bigger); competition between the four state schools; "Loco parentis"; depends on the times; has the best of intentions; big change in role since WW II; Expansion of the school; is a result of the expanding student body; student body became more diverse w/ different ideas; Memorable students; Experience of being at WestConn; all positive and no negative; Physical condition of students; fewer people were oriented to this type of college; smaller school allowed for them to address any physical problems; can remember of two cases in which physical condition became issue
      - Dr. Alfred Geddes (interview) Creator: Geddes, Dr. Alfred Interviewer(s): (no name given) Interview location: unknown Running time: 60 min., ca.Jun 14, 1905; 38941; Number of tapes:1 [tape stock length: 90 minute] (Box 10, Item 24)
        Coverage: 1937-1990s
        Topics discussed: (side A): Dean of Men; different environment in beginning; school had role of "loco parentis"; dorm space was limited (only for women); had task of locating housing for the men; Men at Western; men before and after WW II were career oriented; first big class w/ men was in 1936 (few during the Normal School years); he came as a professor in 1937, left during war, and came back after; WW II changes; male students brought back diversity of experiences; faculty expanded w/ the student body expansion; many came in under GI Bill; became Dean of Men after war; Campus tone; attitude of the women rubbed off on the men; Standout students; Dr. Truman Warner; Welfare of students; was the focal point of the deans; making sure they were housed and feed; take care of any problems they might have; History of WestConn; Danbury Normal School (2 year program to 3 year); Danbury State Teacher's College to Danbury State College; change came w/ addition of new programs; Dr. Jenkins; president of college when he began; followed Dr. Higgins and Dr. Perkins (whom he didn't know); Dr. Jenkins died in 1946 and Dr. Haas, who had been Dean took over; Dr. Haas; she was very interested in development of male students; it was the "Golden Age" of WestConn when she came in; Olympics; went as a spectator to the 1932 games in Los Angeles; Men's Basketball team; he was the second coach (Mr. Pilkinton was first); always hated to play New Britain and New Haven; Music department; Students from outside area; students from far away were coming to the college; many girls followed their boyfriends up north, many of whom went to West Point, and came here; Harvey Jessup; he came in for the expansion of the sports program (except football); coach of the baseball and basketball teams; his players were fully behind; left to take position at Tulane; when he returned for visit, old players greeted him; Ed Rosenberg coached soccer after he left; Physical education; early days, preparing teachers for the responsibilities of elementary education teacher; students needed diversity in their educational background; Disciplinary actions; rare in the beginning; problems didn't occur until later; Feeling of men entering the college; they were career oriented; Activities; proms and dances that brought men and women together; drama productions; Quality of teaching; school size didn't allow for many scholars, but had high quality teachers; Female teachers; when men came, three women teachers were very interested in establishing them as teachers; More about Dr. Haas; "Golden Years" of college; became president after Dr. Jenkins died; college expanded (Old Main and Fairfield only buildings in beginning); Student Union; original was a Quonset Hut; act at snack bar there; Claire Geddes; she was the Dean of Women; she worked w/ architects in developing buildings; she made great contributions to the school; Dr. Haas and school; took great interest in the students; she had lived in Fairfield Hall while she was Dean of Women; Sports programs; basketball grew (side B): Sports programs (cont.); emphasis on winning; travel was always a problem; Playing on the road; time in New Haven when they played Yale Trinity School; went to see a hockey game after; played a Teacher's College in Vermont (loss by one point); Al Thomas; followed Harvey Jessup; was here same time as Bill Williams (who died at young age); Gym; originally in Old Main (now offices); known as a matchbox because of its small size; practiced basketball there; 1960s; disciplinary problems weren't a major problem; since community changed, students weren't a disruption; Changes at college; new faculty and expansion of student body; expectation of college student changed; had been come and graduate in four years, but now many stay longer; many stated coming here to get higher GPA for another college; Dr. Cook; was dean of the college; as new semester began, he always had line of students outside his door of students who had flunked; Tuition; have played role in where students go
      - Dr. Jonathan Greenwald (interview) Creator: Greenwald, Dr. Jonathan Interviewer(s): James Litwin and Eileen Curran Interview location: Midtown campus Running time: 55 min., Apr 29, 1998; 38940; Number of tapes:1 [tape stock length: 60 minute] (Box 10, Item 27)
        Coverage: 1959-1998
        Topics discussed: (side A): History of WestConn; transition from a Normal School to a college; Creating Humanities program; Personal schooling; Reasons for coming to WestConn; Humanities program; Great Brooks program and Columbia University program; evolution at Western; Literature in Humanities; Music and Art; Social Man; History of the Interdisciplinary Department; Program of the 1990s; Personal History; work experience, military experience; living in California; meeting his wife; deciding to go into teaching (side B): Change in students; business majors began to come to humanities classes disinterested; had few bad experiences w/ students; Truman Warner; considered him his best friend; Library committee; was asked by Dr. Haas to be chairman of the committee; library in Old Main didn't meet standards and needed to build one; suggested hiring an architect specializing in libraries to survey area; the library they got was a complete disaster; no one from the committee was invited to groundbreaking; Leaving WestConn; retired in 1985 and didn't return until after his wife died in 1991; came back at urging of Dr. Janick and Dr. Warner; Changes at WestConn; only connection to students through professors; Returning to WestConn; Hopes for WestConn; that it would continue to be better; Benefits of WestConn; great teachers; smaller classrooms; better connections w/ professors; Library and textbooks; New Library; will be building a swing space to house books while building new one; have to tear old one down and rebuild; should start this fall (1998); plans for a new science building are also in the works; School land; proposed to move campus to Fairfield Hills Hospital; felt there was enough land and space to do so; beautiful land; there was also a proposal to purchase land near Poverty Hollow Road in Newtown, but turned down; Westside purchased after other proposals failed; State attitudes towards WestConn; Final comments; his wife's death; return to WestConn
      - Dr. Jonathan Greenwald (interview) Creator: Greenwald, Dr. Jonathan Interviewer(s): Dave Bender and Hank Saver Interview location: Midtown campus Running time: 50 min., ca.Jun 18, 1905; 38939; Number of tapes:1 [tape stock length: 60 minute (micro cassette)] (Box 10, Item 28)
        Coverage: 1959-1990s
        Topics discussed: (side A): Beginning at WestConn; part; time summer of 1959; full; time starting fall of 1959; retired at age 70 because of state mandate; Why WestConn; needed a job and knew someone here; they recommended Dr. Haas and the college; Rhode Island School of Design; a private institution; worked there before WestConn as a department chair; political problems led to him leave; WestConn; when he came, the school was still a teacher training school; had just changed name to Danbury State College; transition to becoming a liberal arts college; Liberal Arts program; helped build it; was chair of the Interdisciplinary Studies (later Humanistic Studies and Philosophy) from 1962; 1978; Changes; in beginning all students were going into education; prior to WestConn, never taught an education class before; Curriculum change; once he started the interdisciplinary studies department, only taught in it; school became divided by the various different departments; Student body; changed gradually; small, primarily education in beginning; larger, various different majors (business and criminal justice popular); Campus changes; just Old Main, Higgins Hall, and Berkshire Hall when he started; still had the Quonset Huts; White Hall was still Danbury high school; library was on top floor of Old Main; Library; had recommended to Dr. Haas that they hire an architect who specialized in designing college/university libraries to survey the campus; Dr. Haas said it couldn't be done; what they got was not good; Dr. Haas; considerable force w/ open door policy; feels politics got the other state college consideration before WestConn primarily because the other 3 had male presidents; Westside; Dr. Haas got an age extension for years to keep working on it; Dr. Bersi came from California and got money from businesses; Ancell school named for such an individual who gave money; Student/faculty relationship; believed it was always good and was warm and never stand; offish; "Nature of Man"; required by all students; took two classes each year first two years and one class each last two; first year was devoted to looking at man as a creature in nature, second was man in art, third was man in society, and fourth man and philosophy; later as each department expanded and wanted own ideas, the "Nature of Man" program was phased out; Department size; 16 at height of "Nature of Man" program; by time he retired, 5 full; time; Vietnam War; National Issues; Name changes of College; reflection of what was already present; questions "university" name because lack of doctorate program; Relationship between WestConn and Danbury; not really sure since he lived in Newtown and worked only in Danbury (side B): Committees; search committee to find new Dean of Liberal Arts (asked by Dr. Bersi); library committee; senate; Library Committee; weren't consulted about chief librarian by Dr. Haas; no one on library committee asked to come to groundbreaking ceremony; Future of WestConn; feels growth would continue; started liberal arts from scratch and was committed to it; Feelings about WestConn now; no ill feelings, but comes back rarely; didn't come back for 5 years after he retired; Dr. Janick and Dr. Warner convinced him to; Student attitudes; significant changes due to size and backgrounds; Race; attitudes on all sides are not that great; grew up in south; story of how his mom scolded him for speaking unkindly about African Americans; when he was a kid and told him to no t look at color of skin rather humanity, which he never forgot; Air Corps; in Biloxi, Mississippi and the treatment they received there; Students; feel they come here because they want an education; some commit too early to a major though; Violin; playing professionally was his wish, but after breaking his fingers in a football game, decided he couldn't; took up chemistry instead, but realized too late he change; Depression; father died during it; also time when he was in college; Harvard; 13 years after he graduated, he asked his former psychology professor, Dr. Raymond Wheeler, for his help in getting doctorate in psychology; Dr. Wheeler helped him get into Harvard; Most memorable moment at WestConn; friendships he has made; starting the interdisciplinary studies program; the occasions when former students come back to thank him